Let's talk about permissions, when each app APK is installed,
it's given it's own unique Linux user ID. And each
app runs within its instance in the Android Virtual machine.
[SOUND] As a result each app is completely sand boxed.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Its files processes and other resources are inaccessible
to other apps. This sandboxing approach is used to
ensure that by default no app can access sensitive
data or perform actions that could adversely impact other
apps, the OS, or users. Things like accessing the
internet, getting the user's location, or reading or modifying
the contacts database. Rather than asking the user each
time an app tries to access something sensitive you
declared permissions that your app requires in it's manifest.
You can get a list of all of the permission
your app may require here at the Android developer site.
So, why not just ask for all the permissions and
never worry about it again? Well, when users install
your app their greeted with this dialogue which lists all
of the permissions that you've requested along with the more
user-friendly descriptions. Nothing says this app was built by hackers
who want to steal my data, rob my house, clear out my
bank account, and take and share nude pictures of me like
a weather app that wants access to every permission on the
device. Best practice is to request the absolute minimum of permissions.
Every time you need to request a new permission, take it
as a flag to stop and consider if there are other
alternatives that might achieve the same goal. For example, using an
intent to launch the camera app, rather than accessing the camera, directly.
Later, we'll look at ways to share your data with
other apps, using intents and content providers to create bridges
between these apps sandboxs. You can declare and use those
permissions in these instances to
similarly restrict access to sensitive information.